Guide to the Pennsylvania Economy League Records, 1925-1985 AIS.1978.06
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pennsylvania Economy League Records
1929-1985
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pennsylvania Economy League
AIS.1978.06
47.5 Linear Feet (38 boxes)
The Pennsylvania Economy League is a not-for-profit organization of business and civic leaders who seek the improvement of government and promote economic development in Pennsylvania. Throughout its existence the organization has provided research services to civic and government entities throughout the state. The records found here consist largely of the various studies and reports produced by the organization.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Pennsylvania Economy League by Judy Eves on February 28, 1978. Additions were made in 1993.
Arrangement
The Pennsylvania Economy League Records are arranged in the following series:
Series I: School District Reports
Series II: Municipal Government Reports
Series III: County Government Reports
Series IV: State (PA) Wide Reports
Previous Citation
Pennsylvania Economy League Records, 1929-1985, AIS.1978.06, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
ACTION Housing, Inc. Records, AIS.2001.11, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Allegheny Conference on Community Development Collection, 1944-1993, AIS.1973.04, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Allegheny Conference On Community Development (Pittsburgh, Pa.), Records, 1920-1993, MSS 285, Library and Archives Division, Senator John Heinz History Center
Pittsburgh, Pa. City Planning Commission Records, 1928-1962, AIS.1976.17, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Scope and Content Notes
The Pennsylvania Economy League (PEL) Records consists of reports and studies completed by the organization for various government agencies. The records inventoried in this guide account for about half of the entire collection of records held by the Archives Service Center. Materials not yet inventoried consist of 46 additional records center boxes. The unprocessed records include PEL newsletters, Allegheny County Airport Advisory Committee minutes, and various PEL files from the Harrisburg (Central Division) Office.
History
The Pennsylvania Economic League (PEL) was founded in 1936 by a group of business and civic leaders seeking to improve the quality of government and promote economic development in Pennsylvania. The PEL emphasizes centers on comparative research and policy analysis. Over their many years of service, the PEL has obtained a statewide reputation for objectivity, integrity, and consensus building. While these principles serve as the general guidelines of the PEL, the specific role of the PEL has changed throughout the decades in order to meet the needs of Pennsylvania.
During the years of the Great Depression, the unprecedented strain and responsibilities placed on state and local governments necessitated that the PEL structure and its programs address these new social and economic concerns, especially regarding public expenditures and taxation. Through the remainder of the 1930s, the PEL worked to establish itself as a statewide research organization as well as a fiscal and administrative consultant and an advisor to public officials. It continued to serve in this capacity during and after World War II, though focus eventually shifted away from social concerns and economic needs when pre-war deficits were replaced with surpluses and state and local debts began to stabilize.
After initially being incorporated with the Philadelphia-based Bureau of Municipal Research in 1936 in order to cut spending, the statewide PEL and the Bureau officially merged in 1954 to become the Pennsylvania Economic League – Eastern Division. In addition to its central offices in Philadelphia, the Eastern Division of the League operated county committees in Bucks, Chester, Delaware, and Montgomery counties. During the 1960s and early 1970s, social services programs expanded with the increase of federal dollars, and the Eastern Division continued to focus on cost-effective government service and the competition for industrial expansion and relocation spreading across the nation. During the 1980s and 90s, the Eastern Division began placing more emphasis on comprehensive, long term studies in addition to day-to-day consulting services for state and local governments and other organizations. Taking a more expansive view allowed the Economy League to begin looking at policy concerns in the context of the Greater Philadelphia region, a complex network of local governments, businesses, and civic organizations. In 2000, the Economy League shifted its primary focus to proactively identifying research areas and initiatives benefiting the region as well as to serve as an incubator for new projects and civic organizing, such as the Greater Philadelphia Leadership Exchange. The Eastern Division was incorporated as an independent LLC of the statewide organization, Pennsylvania Economy League, Inc. in 2005 and was renamed Pennsylvania Economy League - Southeastern PA. To better reflect its emphasis on the prosperity of the region, which includes southeastern Pennsylvania, southern New Jersey, and northern Delaware, in January, 2007, the organization changed its name to the Economy League of Greater Philadelphia.
While the Eastern Division was focusing on the economic needs and developments of Southeastern Pennsylvania and the Greater Philadelphia region, the PEL's Western Division focused primarily on the developments of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County. During the 1950s, the Western Division played a key role in Pittsburgh's Renaissance, working closely with the Allegheny Conference on Community Development. Additionally, the Western Division's studies and recommendations also resulted in the development of ACTION-Housing, Pittsburgh-based non-profit organization that provides affordable housing and related social services. Throughout the 1960s and 1970s, the progressive expansion of public functions and programs produced a growing need for larger management consultation services and research projects, which PEL stepped in to provide. It continued to perform day-to-day routine services, but also worked on projects such as the development of the United Way in Allegheny County and the formulation of recommendations that helped to form the Allegheny County Department of Administration.
Western Division efforts during the 1980s and 1990s include the successful promotion of the new Pittsburgh International Airport and efforts to improve of the government of Westmoreland County. In 1982, the Western Division published a two-year study documenting that the City of Pittsburgh was a "regional city with a local tax base" (Pittsburgh acts as a job provider for the whole region while only collecting tax revenue from the city itself). As a result of this finding, in 1993 a PEL report endorsed the idea of a regional asset district funded by a local sales tax, as well as the use of a sales tax as an appropriate substitute for the personal property tax. This local option sales tax was implemented in Allegheny County in 1994. In 2000, the PEL Western Division—now known as the Pennsylvania Economy League of Greater Pittsburgh (PELGP)—entered into a joint venture with the Allegheny Conference on Community Development, the Greater Pittsburgh Chamber of Commerce, and the Pittsburgh Regional Alliance (PRA), which brought the four organizations together under a common Chief Executive Officer. The relationship was formalized into a strategic affiliation in 2003, with a single membership, staff, and strategic plan supporting and guiding the activities of all four affiliates under the leadership of the Allegheny Conference's board of directors. The structure plays to the strengths of each organization – the research and analysis expertise of PELGP, the advocacy efforts of the Chamber, and the marketing intelligence capabilities of the PRA. These strengths, guided by private sector leadership, is seen as a model for regional improvement.
The Central Division of the PEL has offices in Wilkes-Barre and Harrisburg that serve central and eastern Pennsylvania, with most work concentrated in Berks County, the Central Penn Area, the Harrisburg Area, the Lehigh Valley, the Northeastern Region, the Lycoming/Clinton Region and York County. The Central Division's primary focus is to provide research, analysis, planning and technical assistance to local governments and school districts.
Currently, the PEL is a non-profit organization financed by memberships from individuals, businesses, associations, institutions and foundations. PEL is chartered under Section 501(c)(3) of the IRS Code as an educational and research organization, and financial support of PEL is tax deductible. In addition to memberships, PEL receives revenue from research services contracted by civic organizations and governmental bodies. The PEL currently has three offices (divisions) across the state—the Central Division, the Economy League of Greater Philadelphia, and the Pennsylvania Economy League of Greater Pittsburgh. Each office has its own governance and agenda specific to its region. Despite the relative autonomy of each office, leadership for the entire organization is provided by a statewide Board of Directors.
(Much of this historical sketch was taken directly from the websites of the Pennsylvania Economy League Inc.--Central Division, the Economy League of Greater Philadelphia, and the Pennsylvania Economy League of Greater Pittsburgh.)
Government; Education; Associations; Municipal government; School districts -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Reports; Transportation; Pennsylvania Economy League
- School District Reports, 1939-1987; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The School District Reports series consists of studies generally created for individual school districts. Studies primarily focus on staffing needs, merger considerations, construction feasibility, budgeting, and a variety of other topics.
  - Pennsylvania, "Dollars for Education: Origin and Sources of School Districts Revenue in Pennsylvania", May, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania, "Handbook on Pennsylvania School Authorities", April, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Albert Gallatin, "Albert Gallatin Area School District: Comprehensive Fiscal and Administrative Study", March, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Aleppo, "Preliminary Study of Reorganization of Nine School Districts in Greene County (Aleppo, Center, Freeport, Gilmore, Gray, Jackson, Morris, Richhill, and Springhill Townships)", September, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Aliquippa, "Proposed Junior High School", January, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Aliquippa, "School Distric the Borough of Aliquippa Tax Collections and Commissions 1955-1962", June, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Aliquippa, "Aliquippa Borough School District Actual and Projected Enrollments 1976-77 to 1986-87", November, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Allegheny, "A Study of the Allegheny Township School District", April, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Allegheny County, "Facts and Figures in Merger and Reorganizations Study of Seven School Districs (Etna, Millvale, and West View Boroughs, Hampton, Reserve, Ross, and Shaler Townships)", December, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Allegheny County, "Merger and Reorganization Study of Six School Districts (Bradford Woods, Franklin, McCandless, Marshall, Pine, Richland Townships)", January, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Allegheny County, "Report of Committee on Public Schools of the Metropolitan Sutdy Commission", December, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Allegheny County, "Report of Committee on Public Schools of the Metropolitan Study Commission", March, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Allegheny Valley, "Proposed Position Classification Plan for All Nonprofessional Employees of the Allegheny Valley School District", April, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Allenport, "A Report to the Allenport Borough School District Presenting Facts and Figures Relative to Jointure Possibilities"Allenport, "A Report to the Allenport Borough School District Presenting Facts and Figures Relative to Jointure Possibilities", April, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Allenport, "A Report to the Allenport Borough School District Presenting Facts and Figures Relative to Jointure Possibilities in Units VI and VIII of the Washington County Plan for the Reorganization of School Districts", October, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Altoona, "Report on the Preliminary Financial Analysis of the School District of the City of Altoona 1940-41 and 1949-1950", July, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Altoona, "Altoona and Logan Township School District Survey: Volume I Basic Report", July, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Altoona, "Supplemenal Report on the Altoona and Logan Township School District Survey: Volume II School Plant", July, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Altoona, "Multiperial Insurance Specifications Altoona Area School District", December, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Altoona, "A Preliminary Report to the Altoona Area School District Relative to the Fiscal Impact and Possible Methods of Financing the District's Proposed Building Program", September, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Altoona, "A Long-Range Developmental Program for the Altoona Area School District Part VI Fiscal Analysis and Projections 1957-58 - 1976-77", March, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Altoona, "Part V Finance Altoona Area School District Long-Range Development Program", January, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Altoona, "Multiperil Insurance Specifications Prepared for the Altoona Area School District", October, 1972
  - Altoona, "Financial Trends and Outlook of the Altoona Area School District 1974-75 and 1984-85", November, 1979
  - Altoona, "Altoona Area School District Actual and Projectd Enrollments 1976-77 to 1986-87", February, 1982
  - Ambridge, "A Proposed Position Classification Plan for Non-Professional Employees of Ambridge Area School District", June, 1967
  - Ambridge, "Merger Potentials or Who Should Merge?", March, 1964
  - Ambridge, "Survey of Custodial and Secretarial Work Assignment and Compensation", March, 1967
  - Amwell, "A Study of School Plant Facilities and Requirements for the School Districts of Amwell, Canton, North Frankline, South Strabane in Washington County", August, 1956
  - Apollo, "Possible Sites for a New Senior High School Building for the Apollo Area and Elders Ridge Joint School Systems", February, 1967
  - Apollo-Ridge, "Method of Comuting and Administering a Uniform Tax Levy on School Districts Crossing Country Lines", March, 1969
  - Apollo-Ridge, "A Study of Enrollment, Staffing and Building Utilization", April, 1980
  - Apollo-Ridge, "Apollo-Ridge School District Actual and Projected Enrollments 1976-77 to 1986-87", June, 1982
  - Armstrong, "Estimated Wage Tax Income for the Armstrong School District", March, 1971
  - Armstrong, "Armstrong School District Projection of Enrollment 1976-77 to 1986-87", June, 1977
  - Armstrong, "A Report on the Re-Assessment of the Real Property in Relation to School Districts within Armstrong County", February, 1958
  - Armstrong County, "Armstrong County School District Receipts and Expenditures 1959-60", April, 1961
  - Armstrong County, "A General Guide to the Financial Effects of School District Reorganization in the Upper County Area", October, 1964
  - Arnold, "A Report on the Business Organization and Administration School District of the City of Arnold", November, 1960
  - Arnold, "Reorganization: A Report on the Practicability of Establishing a Administrative Unit for the Members of the Boards of Directors of Arnold City and Lower Burrell Township School Districts", April, 1959
  - Avella, "An Analysis of Various Methods of Allocating Building Costs Amoung Member Districts of the Avella District Joint School System", April, 1959
  - Avella, "Custodial/Maintenance and Clerical Staffing Needs Avella Area School District", May, 1983
  - Avonworth, "A Merger Study Comprising the School Districts of Avonworth Union, Avalon Borough, Bellevue Borough, Ohio Township", October, 1954
  - Baldwin, "The Baldwin Township School District Allegheny County Fiscal and School Plant Analysis"Baldwin, "The Baldwin Township School District Allegheny County Fiscal and School Plant Analysis", January, 1953
  - Beaver County, "The Earned Income Tax Resolution of the Beaver Area School District", June, 1954
  - Beaver County, "Revenue Limitations Under Act 481, June 25, 1947 and Amendments Beaver County Municipalities and School Districts", July, 1958
  - Beaver County, "Beaver County 1958 Market Values & Assessed Valuations Taxable Real Property Beaver County School Districts and Counties of Pennsylvania", July, 1959
  - Beaver County, "Assessments and Tax Rates Beaver County Municipalities and School Districts", October, 1963
  - Beaver County, "Alternative Methods of Student Transportation for the Beaver Area School District", December, 1974
  - Bellmarette, "A Study of the School Plant Facilities Bellmarette Joint School District", June, 1953
  - Bellwood-Antis, "Multieril Insurance Specifications (Section I) Automobile Liability and Physical Damage Specifications (Section II)", April, 1968
  - Berks County, "Improving School Administration in Berks County", February, 1952
  - Berks County, "A Progress Report on County Schools", January, 1955
  - Bethel, "Study Pertaining to the Establishment and Maintenance of a Joint School System", October, 1955
  - Bethlehem (Northhampton County), "The Financial Impact of Merging School Districts in Administrative Unite XII", 1962
  - Big Beaver Falls, "A Comprehensive Analysis of the Operations of the Big Beaver Falls Area School District", April, 1981
  - Blair County, "A Reappraisal of Real Estatein in Blair County", May, 1958
  - Blair County, "The Impact of the Reassessment Program on the Taxing Powers of Blair County's Municipalities and School Districts", February, 1959
  - Bloomsburgh, "Area Planning for Improved School Administration Bloomsburgh-Scott Township Area Columbia County", August, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Bowanstown, "A Condensed Report on Joint Secondary School Operation Bownmanstown Lwr. Towamensing & Palmerton", May, 1950
  - Brandy (Butler County): "A General Guide to the Fiscal Effects of School Reorganization in Butler County (Brandy, Franklin, Har-Mar, Island, Muddy Creek, Portersville, Prospect, Slippery Rock, West Liberty and Worth)", July, 1964
  - Brackenridge, "A Report to the Board of Education of the Brackenridge School District", April, 1946
  - Brackenridge, "Brackenridge Borough and Tarentum Borough School Districts a Consolidation Study", July, 1947
  - Brackenridge, "Facts and Figures Re-Merger and Reorganization of Six School Districts in Northeastern Allegheny County", November, 1947
  - Brackenridge (Upper Allegheny Valley County), "School District Reorganization in the Upper Allegheny Valley (Brackenridge Borough, East Deer-Frazer Union, Fawn Township, Harrison Township, Tarentum Borough, West Deer Township)", May, 1962
  - Brackenridge, "A General Guide to the Fiscal Effects of School Districts Reorganization in Upper Allegheny County (Brackenridge Borough, Fawn Township, Harrison Township, Tarentum Borough, East Deer-Frazer Union, West Deer Township)", June, 1964
  - Braddock, "Administrative and Fiscal Study of the District of the Borough of Braddock Allegheny County", April, 1948
  - Braddock, "A General Guide to the Fiscal Effects of School Reorganization in Allegheny County Administrative Unit #16 (Braddock, North Braddock, East Pittsburgh, Rankin, Turtle Creek Boroughs)", April, 1964
  - Bradford, "Report of the Financial Operations and Business Administration of the Bradford City School District", September, 1944
  - Bristol, "A 'Boom Area' Community Studies its Present and Future Needs", March, 1953
  - Bristol, "Bristol Township Schools Problems and Prospects: A Survey of School Fisciliteis Enrollment, and Financing and Recommendations", March, 1956
  - Brownsville, "School Attendance Areas and Teacher Assignment in Proposed Six-District Jointure", May, 1957
  - Brownsville, "Financial Effects of Jointure Opoeration on School Districs in the Brownsville and Perryopolis Areas", February, 1958
  - Brownsville, "Brownsville Area School District Projection of Enrollment 1976-1977 – 1980-81", June, 1976
  - Brownsville, "Brownsville Area School District Actual and Projected Enrollments 1977-78 to 1987-88", October, 1982
  - Bruin (Butler County), "A General Guide to the Fiscal Effects of School Reorganization in Butler County Administrative Unit No. II (Bruin, Chicora, Clay, Donegal, Fairview, Karns City, Moniteau, Parker, Perry, Petrolia and West Sunbury)", June, 1964
  - Burgettstown"Fiscal Analysis and Projection of the Burgettstown Area School District", November, 1967
  - Burrell, "Burrell School District Actual and Projected Enrollments 1978-79 – 1988-89", September, 1983
  - Butler, "A Comprehensive Educational Survey of the Butler Area Joint School Districts, Volume. 1", 1952
  - Butler, "A Comprehensive Educational Survey of the Butler Area Joint School Districts Volume II", 1952
  - Butler, "Preliminary Report to the Butler Area Joint Senior High School Board on a Financial Study of Member Districts", July, 1956
  - Butler, "A Report to the Butler Area Joint Senior High School Board Concerning the Financial Impact of the Proposed New High School", February, 1957
  - Butler, "Preliminary Statement Regarding the Building Programs of the Nine School Districts of the Butler Area Joint Senior High School", June, 1957
  - Butler, "Review of Local Taxes & Tax Sources for: County of Butler, City of Butler, Township of Butler, Butler Area School District", January, 1977
  - Butler City, " The Proposed 1941-42 Budget of the Butler City School District"
  - Butler City, "Report of the 1943-44, 1944-45 Butler City School District", 1945
  - Butler City, "Report on the 1945-46 Budget of the Butler City School District"
  - Butler City, "A School Study: Consolidation, Organization, and School Plant Requirements", December, 1946
  - Butler City, "A Financial Review of Eight School Reorganization Plans", November, 1950
  - Butler City, "Supplement to A Financial Review of Eight School Reorganization Plans", 1951
  - Butler City, "Findings and Recommendations School Patrol Guard Service Butler, Pennsylvania", November, 1964
  - Butler City, "A Study and Evaluation of the Fiscal and Administrative Operations of the Butler Area School District Phase I", June, 1977
  - Butler County, "A General Guide to the Fiscal Effects onf Reorganizing Butler County School Districts into a County Wide Unit", July, 1964
  - Butler County, "A Reevaluation of Insurance Procurement for the Butler Area School District", February, 1973
  - Butler County, "A Comprehensive Fiscal and Administrative Study of the Butler Area School District", December, 1977
  - California, "The Financial Ramifications of A Five District Merger in Administrative Unite XII", 1961
  - California (Washington County), "A Model System for Scheduling the Work of a Custodial Staff", March, 1970
  - Canton, "Canton Township School District Survey of Elementary School Plant", August, 1959
  - Canton, "An Analysis of the Canton Township School District 1962-63", July, 1962
  - Carmichaels, "Carmichaels Area School District Actual and Projected Enrollments 1976-77to 1986-87", November, 1981
  - Centerville (Washington County), "Preliminary Study of Reorganization of Seven School Districts in Washington County: Centerville, Deemston, Marianna, Beallsville Boroughs, East Bethlehem, West Bethlehem, and West Pike Run Township", January, 1951
  - Central Greene, "A Pupil Projection Study of the Central Greene School District", January, 1964
  - Central Greene, "A Review and Forecast of School Fiscal Operations in the Central Green School District", November, 1964
  - Central Greene, "Personnel Rules and Regulations Central Greene School District", June, 1972